



Yannick Lemin

Nationality: Belgian Date of birth: 05/11/1979 Gender: Male

• Home: Rue Haute Pierrée 2a, 1357 Hélécine (Belgium)

ABOUT ME

Freelance software engineer and architect for a decade, and over 24 years of experience in software engineering, I've had the opportunity to work with many technologies, in many industries, for many purposes.

I spent my early career doing C++ cross platform applications, then moving on to back-end and web development, mostly using JVM technologies.

When the first mobile phone showed up, I was immediately drawn to it and I was very happy to spend 12+ years working as an Android developer and architect.

After this long period, it was time for me to move away from front-end things, and discover the cloud. I am also very interested in LLMs and AI integration, and working on teaching myself those skills.

WORK EXPERIENCE

Senior Software Engineer (Freelance)

BNPParibas Fortis [01/09/2024 - Current]

City: Brussels | Country: Belgium

- Member of the backend team in mobile tribe, working on an Java / Kotlin application which purpose is to interface with third party provider and manage their services from the mobile app.
- Maintainer of lots of different kinds of tests, such as unit tests, api tests (end to end using restAssured), performance tests (using Gatling).
- Transforming Java backend application to Kotlin.
- Feature technical analysis, architecture and refinement.

Senior Software Engineer (Freelance)

Belfius [01/04/2022 - 31/08/2024]

City: Brussels | Country: Belgium

- Member of a support team for which role was to work on the Spring Boot platform, help development teams to be as efficient as possible for development and deployment of micro-services on Microsoft Azure cloud.
- Creation of libraries, part of the platform, to help efficiency and reduce boilerplate
- Creation of centralized pipeline system to simplify the DevOps for the development teams
- Creation of a scaffolder application to help the development teams create new applications and reduce boilerplate
- Worked with Azure cloud services, Azure Devops, Kubernetes, Istio, ...
- Monitoring with Spring Boot actuators, Jaeger, Azure Monitor

Senior Android Developer / Architect (Freelance)

DPG Media [01/01/2020 – 24/03/2022]

City: Vilvoorde | Country: Belgium

- General development and maintenance of 2 media apps based on the same code base
- · Architected new features in order to integrate them best with overall infrastructure
- Implementation of Clean Architecture
- Integration of multiple SDK
- Worked on Video player

Senior Android Developer / Architect (Freelance)

Belfius [31/07/2016 - 30/12/2019]

City: Brussels | Country: Belgium

- General development and maintenance of their main banking application (1M monthly active users on Android) in Java, Kotlin and occasional C++
- New feature development
- Technical advisor for architecture solutions
- Major refactoring of several legacy lower level monolithic layers intomodular components (network communication, security, dependencyinjection, ...)
- Creation of custom views, one of them being a custom layout manager forRecyclerView
- Integration of many 3rd party SDKs, such as video calling, contactlesspayment, 2 step authentication frameworks, etc.
- NDK development in C++
- Setup of automated tests

Senior Android Developer / Architect (Freelance)

Portima [14/07/2014 – 30/07/2016]

City: Brussels | Country: Belgium

- General development and maintenance of multiple insurance oriented applications using Java
- Integration of development best practices in the team
- Moved from separate app tablet / phone to a universal app
- Full refactoring of the network communication and security layer
- Integration of USB card readers used to read Belgian electronic Id cards in the app, information used to fill up forms and electronically signdocuments
- Creation of various library used in multiple apps
- Setup automated tests in the project, and put in place CI with Jenkinsrunning unit and integration tests, experimented a bit with automated deployment in the Play Store

Senior Web Developer (Freelance)

Cullen International [31/03/2014 – 13/07/2014]

City: Namur | Country: Belgium

- Web development in a Java back-end and Javascript with Angular
- Integration of a Angular JS front-end in an existing java based webapplication
- General bug fixing and maintenance of the application
- Help with redefining process for certain aspect of the app

Senior Architect, Web and Android Developer (Employee)

Octo Technology [14/06/2012 – 30/03/2014]

City: Brussels | Country: Belgium

- Architect and Lead Developer for Alpha Credit: GWT front-end with Java back-end application. Coaching of the team, introduction of development best practices and agile methods
- Android Developer for BNP Paribas Hello Bank application. Part of a large team, worked on various features, custom views, communication layer, security
- Research and Development into secure message transmission using NFC and Bluetooth on Android
- Android developer for the Keytrade Banking app, including general refactoring and code improvement, creation of custom views, introduced unit testing in the project
- Android developer for La Poste in France, integrating a large team, working on all aspects of the app and improving code practices and coaching other team members

Senior Java Developer (Employee)

Getronics [14/03/2011 - 13/06/2012]

City: Brussels | Country: Belgium

- Java developer and architect on multiple apps for Belgium's Ministry of Finances
- Android development of a sharepoint client to demonstrate interfacing was possible, even with Microsoft's non standard authentication protocol

Web / Java Developer (Employee)

Emakina [31/03/2007 – 13/03/2011]

City: Brussels | Country: Belgium

- Java developer and architect on the Truvo's MySite project, which is a CMS specifically designed for Truvo's new business model
- Android development of a proof of concept of interfacing the Truvo's MySite CMS to a mobile app
- Java developer on a YouTube like application for Caterpillar
- Lead Java developper and architect for the Samsung's MySamsung project
- Java developer on numerous web projects for different type of customerssuch as banks, energy companies, advertisement, etc
- Android development of the first Electrabel mobile app

C++ Engineer (Employee)

Scheduling Systems Inc. [14/11/2000 – 14/03/2007]

City: Waltham, MA | Country: United States

- Development of a cross-platform airplane scheduling application
- C++ and Ot library
- Oracle Database
- Worked on Unix (HP and Solaris), Linux and Windows
- Also helped setup the development infrastructure and environments in the company (scripts, computer setup, etc)

EDUCATION AND TRAINING

Bachelor of Computer Science Software Engineering

Haute Ecole Rennequin Sualem (Inpres) [31/08/1997 – 29/06/2000]

City: Seraing | Country: Belgium

LANGUAGE SKILLS

Mother tongue(s): French

Other language(s):

English

LISTENING C2 READING C2 WRITING C2

SPOKEN PRODUCTION C2 SPOKEN INTERACTION C2

Levels: A1 and A2: Basic user; B1 and B2: Independent user; C1 and C2: Proficient user

DIGITAL SKILLS

Android Studio / Intellij / Git / Java / SQL / XML / JSON / Linux / Maven / MySQL / Scrum / Android / Spring / Spring Boot / Spring Security / OpenId / HTML / CSS / Javascript / REST / Kotlin / Gradle / Hibernate / Docker / JPA / Jenkins / Microservices / Unit Testing / Swagger / Kubernetes